Finding aid for the Wanda Coleman papers LSC.2282
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 2: Works by Wanda Coleman, 1961-2012
  - Nonfiction, 1973-2012
    - "Blues", 2000-2001 (Box 128, Folder 6-7)
    - Drafts, 2002-2009 (Box 128, Folder 8)
    - Drafts, 2010 (Box 128, Folder 9)
    - "Ruminations on Riots", 2012 (Box 129, Folder 1)
  - Spoken Word, TV, Film, and Theater, 1970-2011
    Contains recorded material from New Alliance records including Coleman's projects with Exene Cervenka, Lydia Lunch, and Michelle T. Clinton; episodes written for popular television shows such as Days of our Lives (for which she won an Emmy), Starsky and Hutch, and Sanford and Son; multiple unproduced screenplays; and plays, including The Product, written in collaboration with Jim Woods of Studio Watts. Includes related correspondence.
    THIS SUBSERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
    - New Alliance Records, 1982-1997 (Box 130, Folder 1-6, Box 129, Folder 5-7)
      Includes materials related to Coleman's spoken word projects with Exene Cervenka, Michelle T. Clinton, and Lydia Lunch; compilations "Black and Tan Club" and "Jazzspeak"; as well as solo recordings "Black Angeles," "Twin Sisters," "Black and Blue News," "Beserk on Hollywood Blvd." and "High Priestess of Word." Includes digital materials.
      Files contain nine 1/8 inch cassettes and one compact disc. Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
    - The Writer's Almanac (recording), 1995 (Box 130, Folder 8)
    - Black Girl in Search of God, c. 1970 (Box 131, Folder 1, Box 130, Folder 9)
      Coleman's adaptation of George Bernard Shaw's play of the same name.
    - Mod Squad and Rose Street, c. 1970 (Box 131, Folder 2)
    - Drafts, 1970-1972 (Box 131, Folder 3-4)
    - The Name of the Game, 1970 (Box 125, Box 131, Folder 5)
    - Ghetto 7, 1971-1972 (Box 131, Folder 6-9, Box 132, Folder 1)
    - Temperature's Rising and Blues Part of Town, c. 1972 (Box 132, Folder 2)
    - The Product, 1972 (Box 132, Folder 3-5)
      Play developed with Jim Woods, president of Studio Watts.
    - Days of Our Lives, 1975-1976 (Box 133, Folder 1-8, Box 132, Folder 6-7)
      Coleman won an Emmy for her writing on Days.
    - Are You Listening To Me Sweetie?, 1975-1990 (Box 134, Folder 1-2)
    - Drafts, 1977 (Box 134, Folder 3)
      Includes episodes co-written with Christipher Joy for Starsky and Hutch and Sanford and Son.
    - Drafts, 1980-1986 (Box 134, Folder 4)
    - Stories/Pitches, 1981-1997 (Box 146, Folder 7)
    - Stories/Pitches, 1990-1999 (Box 134, Folder 5)
    - Shawshi/Independently Blue, 1970-1991 (Box 134, Folder 6-8, Box 135, Folder 1-7, Box 136, Folder 1-5)
      Coleman developed this story as both a screenplay and a novel under these two titles.
    - Operation Move: The Trial of Ramona Africa (research), c. 1990 (Box 136, Folder 6-8)
    - Operation Move: The Trial of Ramona Africa, 1990-1992 (Box 137, Folder 1-8, Box 147, Box 138, Folder 1-7, Box 139, Folder 1-5)
    - Duke of Earl, 1992 (Box 139, Folder 6-8, Box 146, Folder 8, Box 125, Box 140, Box 141, Folder 1-3)
    - Angel Street, c. 1992 (Box 140)
    - Boom Generation (work draft), 1993-1994 (Box 148, Folder 1-4, Box 149, Folder 1)
    - Boom Generation, 1992-2000 (Box 140, Box 142, Folder 1-6, Box 141, Folder 4-7)
    - Boom Generation (correspondence), 1992-1994 (Box 143, Folder 1-3)
    - Drafts, 1992-1993 (Box 143, Folder 4)
      Includes Angel Street episode.
    - Maximum Feedback, 1994-1999 (Box 143, Folder 5)
    - Rimbaud's Demon (work draft), 1997 (Box 148, Folder 5-7)
    - Rimbaud's Demon, 1998 (Box 143, Folder 6-8, Box 144, Folder 1-4)
    - Rimbaud's Demon (correspondence), 1998 (Box 144, Folder 5)
    - Heartbreak's Angel, 2000 (Box 149, Folder 2)
    - Drafts and Renfield, 2000-2010 (Box 144, Folder 6)
    - Renfield (working script), 2010 (Box 144, Folder 7)
    - Renfield (rough, Coleman edit), 2010 (Box 144, Folder 8)
    - Renfield (rough 2), 2010 (Box 145, Folder 1)
    - Renfield (second draft), 2010 (Box 145, Folder 2)
    - Renfield (third draft), 2010 (Box 145, Folder 3)
    - Renfield (final), 2011 (Box 145, Folder 4)
    - Renfield (correspondence), 2008-2011 (Box 145, Folder 5)
    - Drafts, 2010 (Box 145, Folder 9)
    - Mr. Bookie (correspondence and first draft), 2011 (Box 145, Folder 6)
    - Mr. Bookie (first and second drafts), 2011 (Box 145, Folder 7)
    - Mr. Bookie (second and third drafts), 2011 (Box 145, Folder 8)
    - Stories/Pitches, 1990-2008 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    - Beulah Land activism, 1969-1980 (Box 146, Folder 2-4)
      Screenplay drafts of Beulah Land, a mini-series about a 19th century Southern plantation and materials/correspondence relating to the Coalition Against the Airing of Beulah Land.
  - Juvenilia and Visual Art, 1961-1998
    Early writings of Coleman's dating from 1961-1971 and a few more recent works of visual art by Coleman. Includes school notebooks containing class assignments, sketches and drawings; a small collection of periodicals, and early stories, poems, and essays.
    - Juvenilia: High School Work, 1961-1963 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Juvenilia: Notebooks, 1963-1969 (Box 75, Folder 2-6)
    - Juvenilia: Famous Writers School, 1968-1969 (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
    - Juvenilia: English 1 assignments, 1971 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Juvenilia: Periodicals, c. 1965 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Juvenilia: Stories and Poems, 1962-1968 (Box 108, Folder 5)
    - Juvenilia: Stories, Poems, Essays, 1966-1970 (Box 108, Folder 6-7)
    - Visual Art, 1997-1998 (Box 170, Folder 1)
      Includes Coleman's piece "Emotional Blackmail," submitted to the Whitney Ray Johnson Exhibition, and some drawings.
- Series 3: Gigs/PR, 1969-2007
  Includes correspondence, ephemera such as programs, flyers, and photographs, and other documentation relating to "gigs" such as readings and lectures, serving as a panelist for various awards and grants, her time as editor of Players Magazine, and teaching jobs. She kept much of this material in "PR" files, and also included is her correspondence with the Guy Joyce PR agency, who she employed for a short time to represent her. Of particular interest are the files from her time at Loyola Marymount University as the Fletcher Jones chair in literature and writing and her correspondence with legal advisors after the university chose not to continue her appointment.
  Series is ordered chronologically. All teaching materials were kept together to maintain original order, and appear at the series' end.
  - Studio Watts, 1969-2010 (Box 150, Folder 1-2, Box 149, Folder 9)
    Includes materials related to Coleman's plays The Product, Black Girl in Search of God (George Bernard Shaw adaptation) produced by Studio Watts; Ceremony of Us (collaboration between Studio Watts and Anna Halprin of the San Francisco Dancers' Workshop, in which Coleman performed); ephemera, and correspondence.
  - Gigs/PR, 1972-1974 (Box 150, Folder 3)
  - Players Magazine (ed.), 1972-1974 (Box 150, Folder 4-7)
  - Gigs/PR, 1979-1982 (Box 151, Folder 1, Box 150, Folder 8-9)
    Includes PR materials related to Mad Dog Black Lady. Folder 9 includes photographs by George Evans of Coleman at the Whisky-a-Go-Go, where she performed in 1982.
  - Gigs/PR, 1983 (Box 169, Folder 6-7)
  - Gigs/PR, 1983-1984 (Box 151, Folder 2-4)
  - Gigs/PR, 1983-1986 (Box 151, Folder 5-7)
  - Gigs/PR, 1985 (Box 152, Folder 1-3, Box 151, Folder 8)
  - Gigs/PR, 1985-1986 (Box 152, Folder 4-6)
  - California Arts Council, 1985-1987 (Box 152, Folder 7)
  - California Arts Council/Midnight Special reading, 1986-1988 (Box 152, Folder 8)
  - Gigs/PR, 1986-1988 (Box 153, Folder 1-6)
  - Gigs/PR, 1989 (Box 153, Folder 7, Box 154, Folder 1-2)
  - Gigs/PR, 1990 (Box 154, Folder 3-6)
  - Community Redevelopment Agency, 1988-1992 (Box 154, Folder 7)
  - Gigs/PR, 1991 (Box 154, Folder 8, Box 155, Folder 1)
  - Gigs/PR, 1992 (Box 155, Folder 2-6)
  - Gigs/PR, 1993 (Box 155, Folder 7-9, Box 156, Folder 1)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1993-1994 (Box 156, Folder 2)
  - Gigs/PR, 1994 (Box 156, Folder 3-6)
  - Gigs/PR, 1995 (Box 156, Folder 7, Box 157, Folder 1)
  - California Arts Council, 1995-1996 (Box 157, Folder 2)
  - Gigs/PR, 1996 (Box 157, Folder 3-4)
  - Gigs/PR, 1997-1998 (Box 157, Folder 5)
  - Gigs/PR, 1998 (Box 157, Folder 6)
  - Gigs/PR, 1999-2000 (Box 157, Folder 7)
  - Gigs/PR, 2000 (Box 157, Folder 8-9)
  - Gigs/PR, 2001 (Box 158, Folder 1-3)
  - Gigs/PR, 2002 (Box 158, Folder 4-7, Box 159, Folder 1-2)
  - Gigs/PR, 2002-2003 (Box 159, Folder 3)
  - Gigs/PR, 2002-2007 (Box 184, Folder 12-13)
  - Gigs/PR, 2003 (Box 159, Folder 4-5)
  - Gigs/PR, 2003-2004 (Box 159, Folder 6)
  - Gigs/PR, 2004 (Box 159, Folder 7)
  - Calendar, 2004 (Box 160, Folder 1-2, Box 159, Folder 8)
  - Gigs/PR, 2005 (Box 160, Folder 3-4)
  - Gigs/PR, 2006 (Box 160, Folder 5)
  - Hurricane Katrina Fundraiser, 2006 (Box 160, Folder 6-7)
  - Gigs/PR, 2007 (Box 161, Folder 1)
  - Gigs/PR, 2007-2008 (Box 161, Folder 2)
  - Gigs/PR, 2008 (Box 161, Folder 3-4)
  - Gigs/PR, 2009 (Box 161, Folder 5-6)
  - Gigs/PR, 2010 (Box 161, Folder 7, Box 162, Folder 1-2)
  - Gigs/PR, 2011 (Box 162, Folder 3-5)
  - Gigs/PR, 2012 (Box 162, Folder 6-7)
  - Gigs/PR, 2013 (Box 163, Folder 1-3)
  - PR: Reviews, 1983-2007 (Box 163, Folder 4)
  - PR: Reviews/Mentions, 1989-2012 (Box 163, Folder 5)
  - PR: Guy Joyce, 1998-2002 (Box 164, Folder 1-2, Box 163, Folder 6-8)
  - U.S.-Chinese Writers Conference, 1986 (Box 164, Folder 3-4)
  - Teaching, 1989 (Box 164, Folder 6-7)
  - Teaching, 1991-1992 (Box 164, Folder 8)
  - Teaching, 1992-1995 (Box 164, Folder 9)
  - Loyola Marymount University, 1992-1996 (Box 165, Folder 3-7, Box 166, Folder 1-3)
    Wanda Coleman held the appointment of Fletcher Jones Chair at LMU from 1994-1996, after which she was terminated. In addition to student work and course materials, evidence toward and correspondence regarding Coleman's desire to file a wrongful termination suit against the university is included.
  - Loyola Marymount University (correspondence), 1994-1995 (Box 166, Folder 4)
  - Loyola Marymount University (evaluations), 1994-1996 (Box 166, Folder 5)
  - Loyola Marymount University (calendar), 1995 (Box 166, Folder 6-7)
  - Loyola Marymount University (budget), 1995-1996 (Box 166, Folder 8)
  - Loyola Marymount University (periodicals), 1994-1995 (Box 167, Folder 1)
  - Loyola Marymount University (campus publications), 1994-1996 (Box 147)
  - Loyola Marymount University (student essays on Coleman), 1996 (Box 167, Folder 2)
  - Loyola Marymount University (legal), 1996 (Box 167, Folder 3-5)
  - Teaching, 1995 (Box 165, Folder 1)
  - Teaching, 1995-1997 (Box 165, Folder 2)
  - Teaching, 1997-2001 (Box 167, Folder 6)
  - Teaching: Manuscripts by Coleman's students (LMU), c. 1995 (Box 147)
  - Chino Prison Workshop, 2000-2001 (Box 167, Folder 7-8, Box 168, Folder 1-2)
  - Teaching, 2002-2004 (Box 168, Folder 3)
  - San Diego State (Fiction Workshop), 2003 (Box 168, Folder 4-6)
  - San Diego State (Poetry Workshop), 2003 (Box 169, Folder 1-2, Box 168, Folder 7-8)
  - San Diego State (African-American Literature), 2003 (Box 169, Folder 3-4)
  - Naropa, 2007 (Box 169, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Memorabilia, 1963-2012
  Includes Coleman's "clippings files," in which she collected newspaper articles; activist materials such as flyers and periodicals; Coleman's magazine collection; a small sample of her personal book collection and copies of some of her own published books; some periodicals in which Coleman was published; photos; and other ephemera such as her Emmy award certificate.
  Series maintains original order. Coleman arranged her "clippings files" both by topic and chronologically.
  - Clippings: Black Women-Health and Science, 1997-2001 (Box 170, Folder 2)
    Includes Coleman's master list of clippings files by topic.
  - Clippings: Health and Science, 1990-2002 (Box 170, Folder 3-5)
  - Clippings: Health and Science-Media and Racism, 1998-2010 (Box 170, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Media and Racism, 1992-1998 (Box 170, Folder 7-8, Box 171, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings: Media and Racism-Racial Incidents, Cultural Nationalism, Related Issues, 1991-2003 (Box 171, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Racial Incidents, Cultural Nationalism, Related Issues, 1998-2003 (Box 171, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Religion and Racism/The Occult/The Church, 1988-2002 (Box 171, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Religion and Racism/The Occult/The Church-Statistics, 1976-1994 (Box 171, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Statistics, 1972-1992 (Box 171, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Women-Related Issues/Sex in General, 1974-2000 (Box 172, Folder 1-4)
  - Clippings: Women-Related Issues/Sex in General-People, 1971-2005 (Box 172, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: People, 1993-2012 (Box 172, Folder 6-7)
  - Clippings, 1963-1972 (Box 172, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1970-1983 (Box 173, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 173, Folder 3-5)
  - Clippings, 2000-2011 (Box 174, Folder 1, Box 173, Folder 6)
  - Activist Materials, 1966-1973 (Box 174, Folder 2-3)
  - Activist Materials, 1971-1983 (Box 174, Folder 4-5)
  - Activist Materials, 1983 (Box 174, Folder 6)
  - Activist Materials, 1980-1989 (Box 176, Folder 1-2, Box 174, Folder 7)
  - Activist Materials: KPFK Folios, 1981-1986 (Box 175, Folder 1-7)
  - Activist Materials: Australia/Aboriginals, 1981-1982 (Box 176, Folder 3-4)
  - Magazines: Bomb, 2001-2004 (Box 176, Folder 5-6)
  - Magazines: Players, 1973-1975 (Box 177, Folder 1, Box 176, Folder 7)
  - Magazines: Journal of Black Poetry, 1969-1971 (Box 177, Folder 2)
  - Magazines: Journal of Black Poetry-Reggae and African Beat, 1972-1983 (Box 177, Folder 3)
  - Magazines: Reggae and African Beat- Essence, 1970-1984 (Box 177, Folder 4)
  - Magazines: Essence, 1970-1971 (Box 177, Folder 5-6)
  - Magazines: Black Magazines, 1968-1984 (Box 178, Folder 1-7)
  - Magazines: Black Magazines-Literary Magazines, 1984-2010 (Box 179, Folder 1)
  - Magazines: Literary Magazines, 1973-1986 (Box 179, Folder 3-4)
  - Magazines: Miscellaneous, 1967-2003 (Box 179, Folder 4-6)
  - Publications, 1974-2012 (Box 180, Folder 1-3)
    Selected periodicals featuring Coleman's work.
  - Publications/Features, 1983-2011 (Box 180, Folder 4)
    Includes selected periodicals featuring Coleman and a CD recording of Coleman and other poets reading at Southern California venues (2011).
    File contains one compact disc. Audiovisual materials in this file will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Photos-Books, 1970-2008 (Box 180, Folder 5)
  - Books (Black Reconstruction in America), c. 1970 (Box 180, Folder 6)
  - Books, 1982-1990 (Box 182, Box 181)
    Box 182 includes copies of some of Coleman's published books: The Dicksboro Hotel (1989), African Sleeping Sickness (1993), Native in A Strange Land (1996), and The World Falls Away (2011). Both Boxes 181 and 182 contain a small sample of Coleman's personal book collection.
  - Awards/Miscellaneous, 1964-2003 (Box 183, Box 180, Folder 7)
    Box 180 includes Coleman's Emmy certificate and other awards; her birth certificate; Super Lotto records; and a piece of wall art. 183 includes plaques, awards, and a board game.